<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>golang on Daniel Mejía Raigosa</title>
    <link>https://daniel-m.github.io/tags/golang/</link>
    <description>Recent content in golang on Daniel Mejía Raigosa</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Jun 2018 21:37:38 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://daniel-m.github.io/tags/golang/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>An Overview of Go Web Frameworks</title>
      <link>https://daniel-m.github.io/2018/06/an-overview-of-go-web-frameworks/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jun 2018 21:37:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://daniel-m.github.io/2018/06/an-overview-of-go-web-frameworks/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Exploration of http servers in Go. The packages under considerations are,
net/http https://github.com/go-chi/chi https://github.com/julienschmidt/httprouter https://github.com/gorilla/mux https://github.com/zenazn/goji/ https://github.com/go-swagger/go-swagger https://github.com/manyminds/api2go https://github.com/labstack/echo https://github.com/go-chi/chi chi is a lightweight, idiomatic and composable router for building Go 1.7+ HTTP services. Designed to support larg REST API services. built on top of context a go package that handles signaling, cancelation and request-scoped values across a handler chain. The features reported in the readme are, Lightweight - cloc&amp;rsquo;d in ~1000 LOC for the chi router Fast - yes, see benchmarks 100% compatible with net/http - use any http or middleware pkg in the ecosystem that is also compatible with net/http Designed for modular/composable APIs - middlewares, inline middlewares, route groups and subrouter mounting Context control - built on new context package, providing value chaining, cancelations and timeouts Robust - in production at Pressly, CloudFlare, Heroku, 99Designs, and many others (see discussion) Doc generation - docgen auto-generates routing documentation from your source to JSON or Markdown No external dependencies - plain ol&amp;rsquo; Go 1.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
